Princeton University Library Collection of Frederick Monsen Photographs circa 1890-1910.: Finding Aid C1539
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University Library Collection of Frederick Monsen Photographs
circa 1890-1910
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
C1539
2 boxes
4.0 linear feet
This is an open collection of photographs by Norwegian-born photographer, essayist, and lecturer Frederick I. Monsen (1865-1929). Photographs primarily depict Hopi and Navajo people, structures, and landscapes in New Mexico and Arizona.
Scope and Contents
This is an open collection of photographs by Norwegian-born photographer, essayist, and lecturer Frederick I. Monsen (1865-1929). Born in Bergen, Norway, Monsen emigrated to Utah Territory with his parents in 1868. Monsen learned photography as a teenager, when he and his father worked as a photographic team for the Denver and Rio Grande Railroad. He began photographing Indians while working for the U.S. Geological Survey in the late 1880s; and took a specific interest in the Native American communities of the Southwest, which he continued to document from the mid-1880s until his death in Pasadena in 1929.
The photographs in this collection primarily depict Hopi and Navajo people, structures, and landscapes in New Mexico and Arizona. Represented to a lesser extent are Paiute, Apache, Pueblo, and Mojave Indians. There are several views of Indian children, shown with and without clothes, in their daily activities. It consists of a portfolio, entitled "The Frederick Monsen Ethnogoraphic Indian Photographs," dating from circa 1890 to 1910, with twenty-five sepia-toned silver prints (approximately 16″ x 20″ in size) as well as 4 loose silver prints of varying size, dating circa 1905 to 1910.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged by accession.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection adheres to a Departmental practice of combining into one collection material of various accessions relating to a particular person, family, or subject.
Purchases include: AM 2014-104 and AM 2015-6.
Appraisal
No materials were separated during 2017 processing.
Related Materials
A photograph by Frederick Monsen can also be found in the Princeton University Library Collection of Western Americana Photographs (WC064).
The Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens: The Frederick Monsen Ethnographic Indian Photographs (photCL 312)
Cliff-dwellings -- Arizona -- Photographs.; Hopi Indians.; Indian children--North America--History--19th century--Photographs.; Indians of North America--Arizona--1890-1910--Sources.; Indians of North America--New Mexico--1890-1910--Sources.; Indians of North America--Southwest, New--1890-1910 -- Sources.; Mohave Indians.; Navajo Indians.; Paiute Indians.; Pueblo Indians.; Photographs -- 19th century; Photographs -- 20th century.; Monsen, Frederick, 1865-1929
- Ethnographic Indian Photographs Portfolio, 1890-1910; 1 box
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  AM 2014-104
  Arrangement
  The photographs have been kept in the order in which they were received. It is unclear whether this was Monsen's original order, or if they were arranged later.
  Scope and Contents
  Each photograph is signed by the photographer and includes a brief, handwritten description on the front, written by Monsen. Most also include handwritten copyright symbols.
  - Hopi Girl. Pueblo of Mishongnovi, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 1)
    Depicts child in doorway with puppy
  - Hoyuchame, Chief of the Taos. Taos Pueblo. New Mexico, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 2)
  - Hopi. Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 3)
    Naked child sits at ladder base
  - Paiute Indians, Nevada, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 4)
    Tepees and a brush shelter.
  - Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 5)
    Wagon and horseriders near rock walls
  - Laguna, New Mexico, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 6)
    View of pueblos in the distance.
  - Hopi, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 7)
    Child behind masonry, next to ladder
  - Hopi High Priest. Pueblo of Oraibi. Arizona, circa 1890-1905; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 8)
  - Isleta Girl, New Mexico, 1890; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 9)
    Smiling girl stands against adobe wall
  - Hopi. Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 10)
    Young woman with whorled hair sits on masonry, feet rest on ladder.
  - Hopi Boys. Walpi (First Mesa). Arizona, circa 1900; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 11)
  - Hopi Children. Arizona., circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 12)
    Group portrait of 10 naked children.
  - Child of Acoma Pueblo. New Mexico, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 13)
    Child with necklace in water.
  - Navajo boys. New Mexico., circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 14)
    2 boys walking in motion
  - Michongnovi. Hopi town. Arizona., circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 15)
    Pedestrians and horse riders on dirt road.
  - Zuni mother and child. New Mexico, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 16)
  - Moancopa. Hopi town. Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 17)
  - Laguna, New Mexico, Indian Pueblo, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 18)
  - Navajo, New Mexico, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 19)
    Child in print shirt sits on dirt
  - Canyon de Chelly, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 20)
  - Hopi Maiden, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 21)
    Likely Popomana (Gray Butterfly), Hopi of the pueblo of Oraibi, Arizona
  - The Rising Sun, Hopi, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 22)
    Naked child climbing a ladder.
  - Mojave Girl, Colorado River, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 23)
    Girl holding a toddler.
  - Navajo Indians, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 24)
    Family portrait.
  - Hopi girl, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 item (Box P-000079, Item 25)
    Naked child sits on masonry wall
- Navajo and Hopi Indians, 1900-1910; 1 box
  AM 2015-6
  Silver gelatin prints of varying size. Titles and other descriptive information provided by dealer.
  - Watching the Eagles Flight. Hopi Boys, First Mesa, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 folder (Box P-000080, Folder 1)
    Shows four Hopi boys on the edge of a mesa cliff. Front signed by Frederick Monsen with copyright symbol; 13.4 x 10.4"
  - Walpi Pueblo, First Mesa, Arizona., 1900-1910; 1 folder (Box P-000080, Folder 2)
    View of pueblo buildings, ladders, and two Hopi Indian men, with the desert landscape beyond. Negative date: circa 1900, Print date: circa 1910, 13.4 x 10.4"
  - Navajo Indian, Hostine Nez, on Horseback. Chinle, Arizona, circa 1910; 1 folder (Box P-000080, Folder 3)
    Portrait. 7.5 x 5.5"
  - Hopiland, Third Mesa, Arizona. A Little Aristocrat. Child of Techunuva, Chief of the Village of Oraibi., circa 1904-1910; 1 folder (Box P-000080, Folder 4)
    Child is sitting on rock at pueblo. Negative date: circa 1904, print date: circa 1905-1910; 7.5 x 5.5"